Okay, good took a while to write so essentially
what we do is we start off with k arms right
and then in the first round okay so median
elimination is going to proceed in rounds
okay. In the first round we pull each arm
some number of times right determined by this
magic quantity. So can people read this magic
quantity it is 1 by ?L/2 the whole square
better log 3 by ?L okay.
So I pull each arm that many number of times
okay and then I estimate their empirical value
right QLA I will estimate it where L indicates
that this is the Q function I am forming at
the LF stage okay. Then what I do is I take
these QLA arrange them in ascending, descending
whatever order I find the median of all these
arms. And then eliminate all those arms whose
values is below the median right I am eliminating.
So this is the set different so I take my
current set SL that these are all the arms
that are under consideration.
So S1 will be all the arms and then I am eliminating
all those arms such that so my QLA is less
than ml where ml is the median at the Lth
level right. And then I change my constants
by magic amounts again. So my ?L + 1 becomes
three-fourths of ?L, ?L itself started as
?/4 okay.
Now it becomes 3/4 of ?/4 and my ?L+1 becomes
?L/2 which already started as ?/2 so it becomes
?/4, and L=L+1 and I keep going until my SL
becomes 1, the number of arms left becomes
one right. So how many rounds will I go block
k rounds because every time I am eliminating
the half the arms right, because I am looking
at the median and I am eliminating everything
below the median.
So I am guaranteed eliminate half the arms
in every round, so I will end in lock K rounds
okay. But the trick to provide proving any
kind of sample complexity here is to show
that okay, this quantity right when I sum
it over this log K rounds is some bounded
quantity right and that gives me the sample
complexity round.
I have already told you what the sample complexity
is going to be, what was it k by ?2log 1/?
some constant by ? so as far as order notations
we can ignore the constant so log 1/?. So
that is what this is going to be the sample
complexity, so I will have to show you that
first. Second in fact first I will have to
show you that this is actually a pack algorithm
right, that it actually gives you a ? optimal
armed with a high probability right.
It becomes a little tricky here, because I
am eliminating half the arms every times.
So now I will have to think about what is
the probability that I have eliminated all
the ? optimal arms right. So I have to, in
some round along the way before I reach the
final round okay I should not eliminate all
the ? optimal arms right.
So what we will do is we will see the trick,
because at the end of the thing is that one
arm left is some ? optimal arm and safe and
that is along the way if I eliminate all the
? optimal arms then I am in trouble. So what
I will do now is to show that at every round
the probability of me doing that is very small.
So small that when you add up the probability
of me eliminating across all the rounds it
is still below ? still below ? so that is
essentially what I am going to try and show
did that make sense. So the every round the
probability of me eliminating all the ? optimal
arms is small, so small that when I add it
up across all the rounds it is still less
than ? okay. So that is essentially what I
am going to what I mean to show.
.
Okay so first theorem that I will state it,
but I will come back and prove this later
is
the median elimination algorithm with takes
??, this is ?? pack okay. So we will prove
this in two parts the first lambda will help
us establish that okay, and then we will have
another result later that will help us establish
the sample complex.
Sample complex is actually trivial and if
you think about it, it is essentially summing
this quantity up right starting from ?/4 and
?/2 and successively changing the value of
? and ? okay. It is just a bunch of algebra
race is just move numbers around and simplify
things you will get it conceptually there
is nothing deep about looking at the sample
complexity. So I said yeah, so I essentially
have to sum up this quantity right for every
arm.
So this will be multiplied by the size of
the arms which will be, which will start with
k and then it will become k/2, k/4 successively
becomes smaller and smaller and likewise the
? and my ? also becomes smaller and smaller.
So the idea is just to submit over L this
quantity and then replace this by a function
of ? and L. I think we can replace ?L right
by a function of ?.
So what is ? 1 is ?/4 what is ?2 3/4?/2?/4
?3 is (3/4)2 so ?L is essentially (¾)L-1x
?/4. So like that so you can write this as
a similar expression for ? and we can essentially
simplify right. So that part is fairly straightforward
so if you have time I will just give you an
intuition to them otherwise you can work it
out easily.
Now the first part is one that requires some
work right. So this is what we will do for
every phase L in the median elimination algorithm
we have the probability. So this requires
a little bit of thought, so what I am saying
so what is this, this is the two best arm
at level L right. So at level 1 I would expect
this to be A* right.
So and the true best arm I am not talking
about the Q right I am talking about Q* here,
so I am talking about the true best arm right.
So in this case I would expect the true this
this should be Q* A* right in level 1, but
in level two itself it could be something
different because I might have lost A* in
the first round itself right.
What I am saying is okay this is the best
I could have done in the Lth round right potentially
right, and what is this, this is the best
I could have done in the L+1th round right.
So the bad cases when this is less than that,
and that means I have eliminated some high-ranking
arms well all I have left or low ranking arms
right.
So the bad cases when this quantity is less
than that quantity right but how much it should
be less right, that is a question we are asking
here. So if I add an ? to this so essentially
I have my, and let us call this J* right that
is a maximum in the Lth level. So I have my
Q* J* here and I have my Q* I* here which
is the K that gives me the max here right.
If I add an ? to this if I add an ? to this
and this is within that that means this is
? optimal when you can consider against that
right, do you see that if an add an ? to this
lower value and the higher value is actually
less than that then it is an acceptable situation,
because the lower value is within ? of the
higher value correct, so this is a good outcome.
So I am saying the probability of the good
outcome is at least 1-? that means the probability
is high okay, do that makes sense the probability
of the good outcome is at least 1-? okay.
Now the thing to notice here is this is not
truly ? this ?L right and this is not ? this
is ?L, so why is that the case because every
round will lose ?L right at most ?L right.
So at the end of the day I should not have
lost more than ? right. So what I am going
to show you is that every round I will lose
?L and my ?L is chosen such that even if you
lose the ?L for every L overall loss will
be ? right. So that because we know that when
the S, in S1 the best number is A* right.
And if you overall loss is less than ? then
at the end of this I will have at least 1?
optimal on left okay, so that is basically
what we are trying to show here. So this relation
makes sense why we are trying to show this
okay. And likewise this 1-?L is there because
at the end of the day if all the events hold
true also my probability must be at least
1-? right.
Therefore, we use ?L and that is the reason
your ?1s and ?1s are already smaller than
? and ?, because if I start off with ? here
and ? here I am gone okay. So third one w
log means ray without loss of generality I
am going to consider L=1 right. So whatever
results I show here will will hold for the
subsequent L right.
So we start off by looking at the first, the
event E1 which is first thing I am looking
at it I am grossly under estimating the true
value right. I mean this should now start
looking familiar to you, because in everything
we have been doing the same thing we start
off by say okay, first thing that has to go
wrong is I grossly underestimate the true
optimal actions value.
And then we will think about okay what happens
if I overestimate the sub optimal actions
value but I start off by say okay grossly
underestimate this right. So what is the probability
of this, now we already have our magic number
here, so substitute everything
so you have the expression here right and
we have the magic number there.
That this K will get cancelled out, again
we have a four problem there so well the square
should be outside I am just writing it down
from the algorithm here, so their results
are wrong right. So it should be ?L2/2 ?(L/2)2
this is a one-sided bound. So the outside
2 will not be there, right so everything will
simplify and you will get ?1/?3 right.
This is the first E1 suppose it does not hold
okay, suppose E1 does not know that it essentially
I have not made a bad mistake under estimating
the best arm right. And since it is maybe
I should have done it slightly differently
I have said without loss of generality consider
L=1, but then I put an A* here which actually
violates the without loss of generality part
okay.
So the A* here is actually the best arm left
at level L that is how we should think of
it, it is not the overall based arm, whatever
be the level L it is a best arm left at level
L and for L=1 it happens to be A* the true
A* right for L=3 and 4 this will essentially
become the best arm at that level.
So I will just put a L there so that you know
what I mean okay. This is the best arm in
the Lth level that is left among all the arms
that is left true best arm in the Lth level
okay. So next I am going to look at the probability
that as well as translation skill this one,
I should put the 2 in the numerator what do
you need for it to cancel out.
?1/2 so ?1/4 no yeah, so this is ?/2 so substitute
that like an ?2/4 ?2 will become ½ so that
is 1/?2/2 so I will get that is all fine okay
good. So I am going to look at this problem
right, so sorry not this, so E1 does not hold
that means that this is kept to right. So
even if E1 where I have underestimated it
so I am saying E1 does not hold that means
that there is no longer an underestimate.
So this is my estimate is within ?/2 right,
but then I am looking at the possibility that
yeah, so with my some Jth arm which is not
?1 optimal right. So that is a condition no,
this shows I know that current estimate in
the electron I am going to decide about eliminating
the electron right in the current round I
am not underestimated my A*L okay.
So which I am within the ? of that, within
?1/2 of the 2A* value right, but then I take
some other arm J which is a bad arm, bad in
the sense J is not ?L close to A* it is a
bad arm right. And I figure out what is the
probability that the Q estimate for that arm
will be greater than the Q estimate for the
A* right.
So if this happens right, then there is a
chance that A* will get eliminated only a
chance right, it has to be in the lower half
not just get bitten by one J but it has to
be in the lower half of the arms right. So
I need at least k/2 or whatever the size of
SK SL/2 bad arms to beat me correct, for me
to eliminate this arm.
And I need at least half of the arms to beat
me not just one arm right, but before we go
to that part, so what is the probability of
this happening. Well so this conditioning
tells us that QLA* is not too bad right. So
what does that mean QLJ has to be more than
?/2 so we remember that figure we do right.
So either this has to be under estimate was
if I would erase the figure, but either the
A* has to be underestimated by more than ?/2
or the A’ has to be over estimated by more
than ?/2 right, here we are conditioning it
on the E1 that A* is not underestimated by
more than ?/2. Therefore, J has to be over
estimated by more than ?/2.
Since this event we have conditioned it as
false, so that even has to be true okay. So
what do we get in that case same thing here,
so kind of skipping a step here but people
are all fine with that right, I am skipping,
rewriting this bond right. So essentially
you will have to now replace this with over
estimating by ?/2 right. In fact I should
probably just make you write that missing
step as a homework.
So that I am sure that people are all comfortable
with the notation nothing more the notation
can get really complex, otherwise the concepts
are very simple, that is I am taking so much
time talking over it and if I could just write
the proof and leave it at that because it
is fairly easy, these things are fairly easy.
So this is for one arm right and like this
I have k arms right, so the probability good.
.
So let now use the same symbols here, I do
not agree with let # bad be the number of
bad arms okay, # bad be the number of bad
arms such that this this condition holds later
# bad be the number of bad arms such that,
that condition holds. So these are the number
of bad arms that are beating the best arm.
So you have this expectation be mod L/2 yeah,
not really but I agree with the mod SL part
but not SL/2 I have a probability for that
happening right. And how many such experiments
I actually mod SL-1 right potentially everything
other than the best arm could be a bad arm
with maximum thing is SL-1 right.
And so it is a cell -1?1/3, so that is the
probability of one arm being bad and one arm
actually for which this first relation poles
for one bad arm and there are SL-1 I am just
making it SLl to make our life easier. So
SL such bad arms so the expected number of
bad arms will be SLx?1/3. Now I want to look
at the probability that # bad
this is why we are going to use the Markov
inequality right.
So I have already written the expectation
here, so I am asking you the probability of
X greater than equal to A is the expected
value of X divided by A right, so this is
less than or equal to the expected value which
is divided by A okay. So what have you shown
there is that if E1 does not hold if I am
good in my estimate for the best arm okay,
the probability that half the I mean, so many
bad arms will beat me is bounded by 2?1/3
right.
But I am also considering E1 as a bad event
that E1 is also bad because my estimate for
the best arm is really bad you know. So all
bets are off in some sense that because I
do not really, I cannot really identify my
best term because it is so bad right, so all
bets are off so E1 is also bad event that
all of this is bad and E1 is also bad.
So what is the total probability of something
bad happening the two together, but they are
you sticking in if you want to use a fancy
term we use the Union bound and then we say
the probability of something bad happening
is bounded by ?1 right. So this bad is ?1/3,
that bad is 2?1/3 and this is actually the
complementary event of E1 in fact I can just
add the probabilities, I do not really need
the Union bound.
So the total probability of something of bad
happening is ?1 right. So that is essentially
what we are started off by saying here. So
the probability of good is 1-? now we have
shown that the probability of bad is ?L, so
the probability of good is 1-? okay. So one
of the nice things about the median elimination
algorithm is that it was one of the earliest
papers to introduce this kind of a round based
algorithms to the bounded literature right.
Now a lot of later improvements on both regret
based case and people trying to play around
with the the pack guarantees all switch to
some kind of round based ideas, you know so
you do a certain number of pulls and then
you eliminate a certain number of arms right,
and then go back and pull the remaining arm
some more and then eliminate some more arms.
So this kind of a round based elimination
methods have become very popular in the Pandit
literature and the meeting our nation is one
of the earliest such round based elimination
approaches then after this is became very
popular and a lot of papers started being
written using this kind of a round based idea
right.
So we have so far what we have shown is that
it is have you shown that it is back what
is it that is fine I mean that I have already
spoken about this lambda is taken as proved
right, this lambda is taken as prove, so you
have to still use the Union bound for every
round that I am eliminating right, so what
we have to show is well I have all these ?s
right, so we have to keep adding them up to
make sure that eventually you are less than
overall you are less than ? right.
So every round the probability of failure
is bounded by ?1 right so for the K rounds
the probability of failure is I mean whatever
the log K rounds the probability of failure
is bounded by summing it up. So ?2 ?/2, ?/4,
?/8 and so on so forth until you reach 1 right,
so that is the summation and not until you
reach log K rounds.
So it will get ?/2logk okay, and the summation
of log will go to ? it is essentially ?x1/2
+one-fourth +one-eighth right if there is
some runs to infinity you will get one, but
the sum is not running to infinity it stops
at some finite time, so it will be less than
1, so the summation will be less than ? proved
right.
So some probability of something bad happening
will be less than ?. So likewise you can show
these same things for the ? right, so at every
level you drop utmost by ?L right. So the
total you would have dropped this ?/4+ so
it is essentially one-fourth plus what is
it three-fourth into one or write ?/4x1+1
fourth and so on so forth right.
3/4L-1 yeah yeah that was also upper bounded
by 1 if you run it to infinite note some and
suppose wanted by 1 if I run the summation
to infinity but you are stopping at some finite
amount so it will be less than ? okay. So
both of that are satisfied that is easy enough,
the harder, the trickier part is to show the
sample complexity right.
It was not hard, it is just algebra can you
let you guys do it or you want me to do the
sample complexity part of the proof as well
no is it depends yeah nobody say depends depends
on what that is a paper keys are in the paper
yeah it is there in the paper you can look
at it. And so I will stop it here for the
pack the pack complexity will come back to
all of this regulator and pack and everything
when we look at the full RL problem at some
point. Now right now for the bandits we will
stop here.